接下来的下一位演说者
our next speaker
是最著名的推动个人计算机革命的企业家
first known as the entrepreneur of the personal computer revolution
时代杂志上刊出的
was named by time magazine
20世纪最有影响力的100个人之一，
as one of the hundred people who most  influence the 20th century else well as
也是2004年、2005和2006年以及2007年
one of the hundred most influential  people of 2004 2005-2006
世界上最有影响力的100人之一。
and again in 2007
这位仁兄本来可以在这里完成学业，
just think what you could have achieved,
如果他在这里再读两年的话。
if you had stayed here another two years.
没错 yeah
他在1973年秋天入读哈佛就已经对计算机科学入迷，
he enrolled at Harvard in the fall of 1973 keenly interested in computer
但却没有一个明确的学习计划，
science but without a definite study  plan
在玩拉德克利夫扑克游戏中悟到了他未来的商机，
in between intense poker games at  Radcliffe he met his future business
他和他的伙伴Steve Ballmer为它们的第一台微软计算机
partner Steve Ballmer and he developed a  version of the programming language
开发出第一个版本的程序语言Basic,并且共同撰写和发表了
basic for the first micro computer and  co-authored and published a paper on
第一篇关于算法语言的论文。
algorithms with computer scientist christos papadimitriou.
这位演讲者是我们学校
our speaker is a  person of many talents.
众多杰出同学中的一位
a close friend in college
通过记录我看到当年他在著名的普特南数学课中打瞌睡，
i'm using the recall seeing him doze off  during the prestigious Putnam math exam
不过尽管如此他仍得了高分。
despite this napping he scored  remarkably well,
在大三时，他停学离开哈佛
in his junior year he took a leave of  absence from Harvard to devote his
1975年开始，同他的朋友Paul Allen全力投入发展微软公司。
energies to Microsoft a company he had  begun in 1975 with his friend paul allen
自2000年以来，他开始把精力放到慈善事业上，
since 2000 he has begun to concentrate on a number of philanthropic endeavors
为各种慈善组织作出非凡的贡献。
making extraordinary donations to  various charitable organizations and
透过梅林达.盖茨基金，为世界上多种科学研究作出贡献。
scientific research programs around the  world, through the Bill and Melinda Gates
在离开母校33年之后，我非常荣幸地
foundation. after a 33-year leave of  absence from his alma matter
介绍您，威廉.盖茨博士！
i am pleased to present to you doctor. William Gates!
（起立鼓掌......）
(Standing Ovation)
谢谢！尊敬的Bok校长，Rubenstine前校长，即将上任的Faust校长，
Thank You president Bak former  president Rubenstein incoming president Faust,
哈佛集团的各位成员，监管理事会的各位理事，
members of the Harvard corporation  and the Board of Overseers members of
各位老师，各位家长，同学们：
the faculty parents and especially the  graduates：
有一句话我等了30年，现在终于可以说了，
I've been waiting more than 30 years to  say this
老爸，我总是跟你说我会回来拿到我的学位的，
dad，I always told you I'd come back and  get my degree.
我要感谢哈佛大学在这个时候给我这个荣誉，
I want to thank Harvard for this honor
明年，我就要换工作了，我终于可以在简历上写
I'll be changing my job next year and it  will be nice to finally have a college
我有一个本科学位了，真不错啊！
degree on my resume.
我为今天在座的各位同学感到高兴，你们拿到学位可比我简单多了。
I applaud the graduates for taking a much more direct route to your degrees
哈佛的校报称我是
from our my part I'm just happy that the  Crimson called me
“哈佛历史上最成功的辍学生”
Harvard's most successful drop out.
我想这大概使我有资格代表我这一类学生发言，
I guess that makes me valedictorian of my own special class
在所有失败者当中，我做的最好，
I did the best of everyone who fail
但我还是要提醒大家，我使得Ballmer也从哈佛商学院
but i also want to be recognized as the guy who got Steve Ballmer to drop out of
退学了。
business school
因此我是一个有恶劣影响力的人，
I'm a bad influence,
这就是为什么我被邀请来在你们的毕业典礼上演讲。
that's why i was invited to speak at your graduation
如果我在你们的入学欢迎仪式上演讲，那么能够坚持到今天在这里的也许会少很多，
if I'd spoken at your orientation you  were of you might be here today
对我来说，在哈佛的求学是一段非凡的经历，
Harvard was a phenomenal experience for  me
校园生活很有趣，我常去旁听我没选修的课，
academic life was fascinating I used to sit in on lots of classes that I haven't
课外生活也很棒，
even signed up for and dorm life was  tripping
我在Radcliffe过着逍遥自在的日子，
I lived up at Radcliffe and career house
每天我的宿舍总有很多人一直待到半夜，讨论各种事情，
there are always a lot of people in my dorm room late at night discussing
因为每个人都知道我从不考虑
things because everyone knew that I didn't worry about
第二天早起，
getting up in the morning.
这使我成了校园里那些不安分学生的头头，我们过从甚密，
that's how I came to be the leader of  the anti social group we clung to each
做出一种拒绝所有正常学生的姿态。
other as a way of validating our rejection of all those social people
Radcliffe是个过日子的好地方，那里的女生比男生多，
Radcliffe was a great place to live  there were more women up there and most
而且大多数男生都是理工科的，
of the guys were mouth science types.
这种状况为我创造了最好的机会，如果你们明白我的意思。
the combination offered me the best odds  if you know what I mean.
可惜的是，我正是在这里学到了人生中悲伤的一课，机会大，并不等于你就会成功。
that's where I learned the sad lesson that improving  your odds doesn't guarantee success
我在哈佛最难忘的回忆之一发生在1975年1月
one of my biggest memories of Harvard came in January 1975 when I made a call
那时我从宿舍给位于Albuquerque的一家公司打了一个电话，
from career house to a company in  Albuquerque new mexico that have begun
那家公司已经在着手制造世界上第一台个人电脑，
making the world's first personal  computer
我提出想向他们出售软件，我很担心他们会发觉我是一个住在宿舍的学生，
I offered to sell them software I worried they would realize I was just a
从而挂断电话，
student in a dorm and hang up on.
但是他们却说:“我们还没准备好，
instead they said we're not quite ready
一个月后你再来找我们吧。” 这是个好消息，
come see us in a month which was a good  thing,
因为那时我软件还根本没写出来呢。
because we hadn't written the software yet.
就是从那时起，我日以继夜地在这个小小的课外项目上工作，
from that moment I work day and night on the extra credit project that marked the
这导致了我学生生活的结束，以及通往微软公司的不平凡的旅程开始，
end of my college education and the  beginning of a remarkable journey with
不管怎样，我对哈佛的回忆主要都与充沛的精力和智力活动有关，
Microsoft what I remember above all about Harvard was being in the midst of
哈佛的生活令人愉快，也令人感到压力。
so much energy and intelligence
有时甚至会感到泄气，
it could be exhilarating intimidating  sometimes even discouraging
但永远充满了挑战性。
but always challenging
生活在哈佛是一种吸引人的特殊待遇，虽然我离开得比较早，
it was an amazing privilege and though I left early
但是我在这里的经历，在这里结识的朋友，在这里发展起来的一些想法，永远地改变了我。
I was transformed by my years at Harvard the friendships I made and the ideas I worked on.
但是，如果现在严肃地回忆起来，
but taking a serious look back,
我确实有一个真正的遗憾，我离开哈佛的时候，根本没有意识到
I do have one big regret I left Harvard with no real awareness of the awful
这个世界是多么的不平等，
inequities in the world
人类在健康、财富和机遇上的不平等大得可怕，
the appalling disparities of health and well an opportunity that condemn
它使得无数的人们被迫生活在绝望之中。
millions of people the lives of despair
我在哈佛学到了很多经济学
I learned a lot here at Harvard about new ideas and
和政治学的新思想
economics and politics
我也了解了很多科学上的新进展，
I got great exposure to the advances being made in the sciences
但是，人类最大的进步并不来自于这些发现，
but humanity's greatest advances are not in its discoveries but in how those
而是来自于那些有助于减少人类不平等的发现。
discoveries are applied to reduce inequity
鼓掌......
yeah
不管通过何种手段，民主制度、健全的公共教育体系，高质量的医疗保健，
whether through democracy strong public education quality health care are broad
还是广泛的经济机会， 减少不平等始终是人类最大的成就。
economic opportunity producing an equity is the highest human achievement
我离开校园的时候，根本不知道在这个国家里，有几百万的年轻人
I left campus knowing little about the  millions of young people cheated out of
无法获得接受教育的机会，我也不知道，
educational opportunities here in this  country and I knew nothing about the
发展中国家里有无数的人们生活在无法形容的贫穷和疾病之中。
millions of people living in unspeakable poverty and disease in developing countries
我花了几十年才明白了这些事情，在座的各位同学，你们是在与我不同的时代来到哈佛的
it took me decades to find out you graduates came to Harvard at a different time
你们比以前的学生更多地了解
you know more about the worlds in equities than the classes that came
世界是怎样的不平等，
before in your years here
在你们的哈佛求学过程中，我希望你们已经思考过一个问题，
I hope you had a chance to think about how in this age of accelerating
那就是在这个新技术加速发展的时代，我们怎样最终应对这种不平等，
technology we can finally take on these inequities and we can solve them
以及我们怎样来解决这个问题，为了讨论的方便，请想象假如你每个星期
imagine just for the sake of discussion that you had a few hours a week and a
可以捐献一些时间，每个月可以捐献一些钱，你希望这些时间和金钱可以用到对
few dollars a month to donate to a cause and you wanted to spend that time
拯救生命和改善人类生活有最大作用的地方，
and money or would have the greatest impact in saving and improving lives
你会选择什么地方？这也是我和Melinda（盖茨夫人）面临的问题。
where would you spend it？ for Melinda and I the  challenges the same
我们如何能将我们拥有的资源发挥出最大的作用，
how can we do the most good for the  greatest number with the resources we have
在讨论过程中，Melinda和我读到了一篇文章，里面说在那些贫穷的国家，
during our discussions on this question Linda and I read an article about the
每年有数百万的儿童死于
millions of children were dying every year in poor countries from diseases
在美国早已不成问题的疾病。
that we had long ago made harmless in  this country
麻疹、疟疾、肺炎、
measles malaria pneumonia
乙型肝炎、黄热病，还有一种以前我从未听说过的轮状病毒
hepatitis B yellow fever one disease that I had never heard of rotavirus was
每年导致50万儿童的死亡。
killing half a million children each year
但是在美国一例死亡病例也没有。我们被震惊了，
none of them in the United States we  were shot we'd assumed
我们想如果几百万儿童正在死亡线上挣扎，而且他们是可以被挽救的，
that millions of children were dying and they could be saved the world would make
那么世界理应将用药物拯救他们作为头等大事。
it a priority to discover and deliver  the medicines to save them.
但是事实并未如此，那些价格还不到一美元的救命药剂
but it did not for under a dollar
并没有送到他们的手中。
there were interventions that could save lives - just weren't being delivered
如果你相信每个生命都是平等的
if you believe that every life has equal value
那么我们无法接受某些生命被拯救了，而另一些生命 却被放弃了。
it's revolting to learn that some lives  are seen as worth saving and others are not
我们对自己说，事情不可能如此，但如果这是真的，
we said to ourselves this can't be true， but if it is true
那么它理应是我们努力的头等大事，所以我们开始行动，
it deserves to be the priority of our  giving. so we began up and begin our work
用任何人都想得到的方式开始工作。
in the same way anyone here would begin  it.
我们问：“这个世界怎么可以眼睁睁看着这些孩子死去？”
we asked how could the world let these  children die?
答案很简单，也很令人难堪。在市场经济中，拯救儿童是一项
by the answer is simple and harsh，the market did not reward
没有利润的工作，政府也不会提供补助。
saving the lives of these children, and  governments did not subsidize it.
这些儿童之所以会死亡，是因为他们的父母在经济上没有实力，
So the children died because their  mothers and fathers had no power in the
在政治上没有能力发出声音。但你们和我两者都具备，
market and no voice in the system. but  you and I have both.
我们可以让市场更好地为穷人服务，
we can make market for forces work better for the poor
如果我们能发展出一种更有创新性的资本主义制度，
if we can develop a more creative  capitalism
如果我们可以改变市场让更多的人可以获得利润，
if we can stretch the reach of market  forces so that
或至少能自食其力，这就可以帮到那些
more people can make a profit or at least earn a living
正在极端不平等的状况中受苦的人们。
serving people who are suffering from the great in equities
我们还可以向全世界的政府施压，要求他们将纳税人的钱
we can also press governments around the  world to spend taxpayer money in ways
花到更符合纳税人价值的地方，
that better reflect the values of the  people who pay the taxes if we can find
如果我们能够找到这样一种方法，既可以帮到穷人，又可以为商人带来利润，
approaches that meet the needs of the poor in ways that generate profits for
为政治家带来选票，
business and votes for politicians
我们就找到了一种减少世界性不平等的可持续的发展道路。
we will have found a sustainable way to reduce inequity in the world.
这个任务
now this task
是无限的，它不可能被完全完成，但任何自觉地解决这个问题的尝试，
is open-ended it can never be finished . But a conscious effort to answer this
都将会改变这个世界。
challenge can change the world.
在这个问题上，我是乐观的，但我也遇到过那些感到绝望的怀疑论者，
I'm optimistic that we can do this but I talked to skeptics claim there is no hope.
他们说，不平等从人类诞生的那天就存在，直到人类灭亡的那天也将存在，
they say in equity has been with us  since the beginning and will be with us
因为人们对这个问题根本不在乎。
until the end because people just don't  care.
我完全不同意这种观点。
I completely disagree
我相信，问题不是我们不在乎，而是我们不知道怎么做。
I believe we have more caring than we  know what to do with all of us here in
此刻在这个院子里的所有人，生命中总有这样或那样的时刻，目睹人类的悲剧，
this yard at one time or another have  seen human tragedies that broke our
感到万分伤心，但是我们什么也没做。
heart and yet we did nothing
并非我们无动于衷，而是因为我们不知道做什么和怎么做，如果我们知道
not because we didn't care but because we didn't know what to do if we had
如何做是有效的，那么我们就会采取行动，改变世界的障碍，
known how to help we would have acted . The barrier to change is not too little
并非由于人类的冷漠，而是世界实在太复杂，为把关心转变为行动，
carrying it is too much complexity to  turn carrying into action
我们需要找到问题，找到解决问题的方法和评估后果，但世界的复杂性使得
we need to see a problem see a solution  and see the impact. But complexity
所有这些步骤都难于做到。
blocks all three steps
即使有了互联网和24小时直播的新闻台，
even with the advent of the internet and  24-hour news
让人们真正发现问题所在仍然十分困难
it is still the complex enterprise to  get people to truly see the problems
当一架飞机坠毁了，官员们会立刻召开新闻发布会，
when an airplane crashes officials  immediately call a press conference
他们承诺进行调查，找到原因防止将来再次发生类似事故。
they promised to investigate determine  the cause and prevent similar crashes in
但是如果那些官员敢说真话，他们就会说，在今天这一天，
the future but if the officials were  brutally honest they would say of all
全世界所有可以避免的死亡之中，只有0.5%的死者来自于这次空难，
the people in the world who died today  from preventable causes one half of one percent.
我们决心尽一切努力调查
we're on this plane we're determined to  do everything possible to solve the
这个0.5%的死亡原因，显然，
problem that took the lives of the one  half of one percent the problem
更重要的问题不是这次空难，而是其他几百万可以预防的死亡事件，
is not just the plane crash but the millions of preventable dad's we don't
我们并没有很多机会了解那些死亡事件，媒体总是报告新闻，
read much about these death, the media  covers what's new and millions of people
而几百万人将要死去并非新闻，如果没有人报道，那么这些事件就很容易被忽视。
dying is nothing new so it stays in the  background where it's easy to ignore
另一方面，即使我们确实目睹了事件本身或看到了相关报道，
but even when we do see it or read about it
我们也很难持续关注这些事件。
it's difficult to keep our eye eyes on the problem
他人受苦是令人痛苦的，何况问题又如此复杂，我们根本不知道如何去帮助他人，
it's difficult to look at suffering if  the situation is so complex that we
所以我们会把脸转过去。
don't know how to help and so we look  away.
就算我们真正发现了问题所在，也不过是迈出了第一步，
if we can really see a problem which is  the first step
接着还有第二步
we come to the second step.
那就是从复杂的事件中找到解决办法，
cutting through the complexity to find a solution
如果我们要让关心落到实处，我们就必须找到解决办法。
finding solutions is essential if we want to make the most of our caring if
如果我们有一个清晰的和可靠的答案，
we have clear improvement answers
那么当任何组织或个人提出“我能如何提供帮助”时，
any time an organization or individual  asks how can I help
我们就能采取行动，我们就能够保证
then we can get action and we can make  sure that none of the caring in the
不浪费资源。
world is wasted
但是，世界的复杂性使得很难找到对全世界每一个有爱心的人都有效的行动方法，
the complexity makes it hard to mark a  path of action for everyone who cares
因此人类对他人的关心往往很难产生实际效果，
and makes it hard for their carrying to matter
从这个复杂的世界中找到解决方法，可以分为四个步骤，
cutting through complexity to find solutions runs through 4 predictable
确定目标，找到最高效的方法，
stages determine a goal find the highest  impact approach deliver the technology
发现适用于这个方法的新技术，
ideal for that approach
同时最聪明地利用现有的技术
and in the same time use the best  application of Technology you already have.
不管它是复杂的新药物，
whether it's something  so phisticated like the new drug or
还是最简单的蚊帐，艾滋病就是一个例子。
something simple like the bed net。 the  AIDS epidemic offers an example the
总的目标，毫无疑问是消灭这种疾病，最高效的方法是预防。
broad goal of course is to end the disease the highest leverage approach is   prevention.
最理想的技术是发明一种疫苗，
the ideal technology would be a vaccine
只要注射一次，就可以终生免疫。所以，政府、制药公司、基金会应该
that gives lifelong immunity with a single dose。 So governments drug
资助疫苗研究，但是，这样的研究工作
companies and foundations are funding vaccine research but their work is
很可能十年之内都无法完成，
likely to take more than a decade.
因此，与此同时，我们必须使用现有的技术，目前最有效的预防方法就是
so in the meantime we have to work with what we have in hand and the best
设法让人们避免那些危险的行为，要实现这个新的目标，
prevention approach we have now is  getting people to avoid risky behavior
又可以使用新的四步循环，这只是一种模式，
pursuing that goal starts the four-step  cycle again this is the pattern
关键的事情是永远不能停止思考和行动，我们千万不能
the crucial thing is to never stop  thinking and working and never do what
再犯上个世纪在疟疾和肺结核上犯过的错误，那时我们因为它们太复杂，
we did with malaria and tuberculosis in the 20th century which is to surrender
而放弃了采取行动，在发现问题和找到解决方法之后，
to complexity and quit.The final step  after seeing the problem and finding an
就是最后一步，评估工作结果，将你的成功或失败的经验传播出去，
approach is to measure the impact of the work and to share that success or
这样其他人就可以从你的努力中学得经验。当然，
failure so that others can learn from  the efforts. you have to have the
你必须有一些统计数字，你必须让他人知道。
statistics of course you have to be able  to show for example that a program is
你的项目为几百万儿童新接种了疫苗
vaccinating million more millions more  children
你也必须让他人知道儿童死亡率
you have to be able to show for example a decline in the number of children
下降了多少。
dying from the diseases
这些都是很关键的，不仅有利于改善项目效果，也有利于
this is essential not just to improve the program but also to help draw more
从商界和政府得到更多的帮助。 但是，如果你想鼓励其他人参加你的项目
investment from business and government.  But if you want to inspire people to participate
你就必须拿出更多的统计数字，必须展示你的项目的人性因素，
you have to show more than numbers. You  have to convey the human impact of the
这样其他人就会感到拯救一个生命，对那些处在困境中的家庭到底意味着什么。
work so people can feel what saving a  life means to the families affected
记得几年前我去参加世界经济论坛，旁听一个全球健康问题会议，
I remember going to the World Economic  Forum some years back and sitting on a
会议的内容有关于如何拯救几百万条生命，是几百万
global help panel that was discussing  ways to save millions of lives millions
想一想吧，拯救一个人的生命已经让人何等激动，现在你要把这种激动
think of the thrill if you could save  just one person's life then multiply
再乘上几百万倍。
that by millions yet
但不幸的是，这是我参加过的最最乏味的论坛，
this was the most boring panel I've ever  been on ever so boring
乏味到令我几欲先走。
even I couldn't stand.
那次经历之所以让我难忘，是因为之前
what made that experience especially  striking was that I just come from an
我们刚刚发布了一个软件的第13版本，我们让观众激动得跳了起来，
event where we were introducing version 13 of some piece of software and we had
欢呼雀跃。
people jumping and shouting with  excitement.
我喜欢人们因为软件而感到激动，那么我们为什么不能让人们因为
I love getting people excited about  software but why can't we generate even
能够拯救生命而感到更加激动呢？
more excitement for saving lives?
除非你能够让人们看到或感受到
you can't get people excited
行动的影响力，否则你无法让人们激动。
unless you can help them see and feel  the impact
如何做到这一点并不是一件简单的事
the way to do that is another complex  question
同前面一样，在这个问题上我依然是乐观的。
still I'm optimistic
不错，人类的不平等有史以来一直存在，但那些能够化繁为简的
yes in equity has been with us forever  but the new tools we have to cut through
新工具却是最近才出现的。
complexity have not been with us forever
这些新工具可以帮助我们将人类的同情心发挥到极致。
they are new they can help us make the  most of our caring and that's why the
这就是为什么未来和过去是不一样的，这个时代无时无刻不在涌现新的变革
future can be different from the past . The defining and ongoing innovations  of this age,
生物技术，个人计算机，互联网，
biotechnology the personal computer and  the Internet
它们给了我们一个从未有过的机会去终结那些极端的贫穷
give us a chance we've never had before  to end extreme poverty and n debt from
和非恶性疾病的死亡，60年前，乔治.马歇尔也是在这个地方的毕业典礼上
preventable disease 60 years ago George  Marshall came to this commencement and
宣布了一个计划，帮助战后的欧洲国家的建设，
he announced a plan to assist the  nation's a post-war Europe
他说：“我认为，困难的一点是这个问题太复杂，报纸和电台向公众
he said quote I think one difficulty is  that the problem is one of such enormous
源源不断地提供各种事实，
complexity that the very massive facts  presented to the public by press and
使得大街上的普通人要清晰地判断形势
radio make it exceedingly difficult for  the man in the street to reach a clear
变得非常困难。事实上，经过层层传播，
appraisement of the situation. it is  virtually impossible at this distance to
想要真正地把握形势，
grasp at all.
是根本不可能的。”
the real significance of the situation
马歇尔发表这个演讲之后的三十年，我那一届学生毕业，
30 years after Marshall made his address  which was 30 years ago as my class
当然我不在其中。
graduated without me.
那时，新技术刚刚开始萌芽，它们将使得这个世界变得更小、更开放、
technology was emerging that would make the world smaller more open more visible
更容易看到、距离更近。
less distance. The emergence
低成本的个人电脑的出现使得一个强大的互联网有机会诞生，
of low-cost personal computers gave rise  to a powerful network that has
它为学习和交流提供了巨大的机会，
transformed opportunities for learning  and communicating the magical thing
网络的神奇之处，不仅仅是它缩短了物理距离，
about this network is not just that it  collapses distance，
使得天涯若比邻，
and makes everyone your neighbor.
它还极大地增加了具有共同想法的人们聚集在一起的机会，
it also dramatically increases the  number of brilliant minds we can bring
我们可以为了解决同一个问题一起共同工作，这就大大加快了革新的进程
into work together on the same problem.  and it skills up the rate of potential
发展速度简直快得让人震惊。与此同时，世界上有条件上网的人
innovation to a staggering degree. at the  same time for every person who has
只是全部人口的六分之一，这意味着，
access to this technology five people  don't，
还有许多具有创造性的人们没有加入到我们的讨论中来。
that means many creative minds are left  out of this discussion.
那些有着实际操作经验和相关经历的聪明人，却没有技术来帮助他们，
smart people with practical intelligence  and relevant experience who don't have
将他们的天赋或者想法与全世界分享。
the technology to hone their talents or  contribute their ideas to the world.
我们需要尽可能地让更多的人有机会使用新技术，
we need as many people as possible to  gain access to this technology because
因为这些新技术正在引发一场革命，
these advances are triggering a  revolution in human and what human
人类将因此可以互相帮助。
beings can do for one another.
新技术正在创造一种可能，不仅是政府，
they are making it possible not just for  national governments but for
还包括大学、公司、小机构甚至个人。
universities corporations small  or ganizations and even individuals to
能够发现问题所在，能够找到解决办法，能够评估他们努力的效果，
see problems see approaches and measure  the impact of their efforts to address
去改变那些马歇尔60年前 the hunger poverty and desperation
就提出过的问题---饥饿、贫穷和绝望。
George Marshall spoke up 60 years ago
哈佛是一个大家庭，这个院子在场的人们
members of the Harvard family here in  the yard is one of the great collections
是全世界最有智力的人类群体之一，
of intellectual talent in the world,
我们可以做些什么？毫无疑问，
for what purpose there is no question  that the faculty
哈佛的老师、校友、学生和资助者已经用他们的能力
the Alumni the students and the  benefactors of Harvard have used their
改善了全世界各地人们的生活，但是，我们还能够再做什么呢？
power to improve the lives of people  here and around the world but can we do
有没有可能，哈佛的人们可以将他们的智慧用来帮助那些甚至从来
more than Harvard dedicate its intellect  to improving the lives of people will
没有听到过“哈佛”这个名字的人。
never even hear its name
请允许我向各位院长和教授提出一个请求，你们是哈佛的
let me make a request of the deans and  the professor's the intellectual leaders
智力领袖，当你们雇佣新的老师，授予终身教职，评估课程
here at Harvard as you hire new faculty  award tenure review curriculum and
决定学位颁发标准的时候，请问你们自己如下的问题：
determine degree requirements please ask  yourself：should our best minds be more
我们最优先的人才是否在致力于解决我们最大的问题？
dedicated to solving our biggest problems should Harvard encourage its
哈佛是否鼓励她的老师去研究解决世界上最严重的不平等？
faculty to take on the world's worst in equity
哈佛的学生是否知道世界上那些极端的贫穷？
in harvard students know about the depth  of global poverty?
世界性的饥荒，清洁水资源的缺乏，
the prevalence of world hunger the  scarcity of clean water
无法上学的女童，死于本可治愈的疾病的儿童，
the girls get out of school the children  who die from diseases we can cure,
世界上过着最优越生活的人们，有没有了解到这个世界最贫穷的
should the world's most privileged learn  about the lives of the world's
人们的生活？
least privilege?
这些问题并非老生常谈。
these are not reported question
你必须用自己的行动来回答它们。
you will answer with your policies.
我母亲在我被哈佛大学录取的那一天，
My mother who is filled with pride
曾经感到非常骄傲，她从没有停止督促我去为他人做更多的事情。
the day i was admitted，her never stop  pressing me to do more for others.
在我结婚的前几天，她主持了一个新娘进我家的仪式，在这个仪式上，
A few days before I was married she hosted a bridal event and when she read aloud a
她高声朗读了一封关于婚姻的信，这是她写给Melinda的，那时，
letter about marriage that she had  written to Melinda my mother was very
我母亲已经因为癌症病入膏肓，但是她还是认为这是又一个
ill with cancer at the time but she saw  one more opportunity to deliver her
传播她的信念的机会，在那封信的结尾，她写道：你的能力越大，
message and at the close of the letter  she said from those to whom much is
人们对你的期望也就越高。
given much is expected.
想一想吧，我们在这个院子里的这些人，被给予过什么，
when you consider what those of us here  in this yard have been given in talent
天赋，特权，机遇，可以这样说，这个世界完全有权
privilege and opportunity there is  almost no limit to what the world has a
期待我们做出贡献，同这个时代的期望一样，
right to expect from us, in line with the  promise of this age,
我也要向今天各位毕业的同学提出一个忠告，
深刻的不平等的问题，然后你们要变成这个问题的专家，
a deep in equity and become a specialist on it.
如果你们能够使得这个问题成为你们职业的核心，那么你们就会非常杰出。
if you make it the focus of your career  that would be phenomenal.
但是你们不必一定要以此为职业，每个星期只用几个小时，
but you don't have to do that to make an  impact for a few hours every week
你就可以通过不断成长的互联网得到信息，
you can use the growing power of the  internet to get informed find others
找到志同道合的朋友，
with the same interests.
并发现困难所在，找到解决它们的途径，
see the barriers and find ways to cut  through them.
不要让世界的复杂性阻碍你前进，
don't let complexity stop you,
在解决人类的不平等事业中做一个积极的行动主义者。
be active activists take on big and  equities
它将成为你生命中最重要的经历之一，在座的各位毕业的同学
I feel sure it will be one of the great  experiences of your lives you graduates
你们所处的时代是一个神奇的时代，当你们离开哈佛的时候，你们拥有的
are coming of age in an amazing time as  you leave Harvard you have technology
技术是我们那一届学生所没有的，你们已经了解到了我们以前所不了解的
that members of my class never hand. You  have awareness of global equity which we
世界上的不平等。有了这样的了解之后，若再弃那些需要帮助的人们于不顾，
did not have, and with that awareness you  likely also have an informed conscience
必将受到良心的谴责。
that will torment you.
只需一点小小的努力，你就可以改变那些人们的生活。
if you abandon these people whose lives， you could change with modest effort you
你们拥有比我们更大的能力，
have more than we had,
你们必须尽早开始，尽可能长期坚持下去，我希望30年后，
you must start sooner and carry on  longer and I hope
你们还会再回到哈佛，回溯你们用自己的天赋和能力
you will come back here to Harvard 30  years from now and reflect on what
所做出的一切。我希望那时，
you've done with your talent and your energy
你们用来评价自己的标准，不仅仅是你们的专业成就，
I hope you will judge your selves not on  your professional accomplishments alone
还包括你们为改变这个世界深刻的不平等所做出的努力，
but also on how well you have addressed  the world's deepest inequities on how
以及你们如何善待那些远隔世界那边的人们，
well you treated people a world away
与你们毫不相关的人们，但他们也是人类！
we have nothing in common with you, but  their humanity!
祝各位好运！
good luck
长时间鼓掌......
Long applause......